At 5.32, I'll call the meeting to order for the Lancaster City Planning Commission. Our first item up for grabs is do I have an approval of the meeting minutes from August 6, 2025?
Motion to approve.
I have a motion. Do I have a second?
Second.
I have a motion and a second. All in favor? Oh, bear with me for one second here. Let's do some housekeeping. Week six for quorum five. Mr. Stevens, or I'm sorry, Mr. Porter. backwards i do uh would you uh be willing to be a voting member this evening i'd be delighted to complete our quorum so uh ladies and gentlemen just to inform you um we will have an alternate member voting as a full member as a member a voting member this evening all right so now we'll call the approval of the meeting minutes for august 6. i have a motion and a second all in favor aye aye aye aye aye any opposed motion carries next item subdivision and land development for 1180 manheim pike conditional approval of the preliminary final plan evening my name is terry dillo i am with
integrated consulting and we prepared the final land development plan that's in front of you this evening we can go through if you have the plans or if we could project the land development plan onto the screen while that's getting set up the site if you're not familiar with it's located 1180 manheim pike it's about a 2.2 acre site within the commercial i'm sorry regional commercial c3 zoning district of the city the plan proposes the demolition anything bigger if anybody want
like if you need me to zoom in i can scroll through pages so just if you tell me where you need to be okay and if you want to see anything more specific i'm happy to zoom in
great which is number two please i apologize did you state your name yes terry dealo with integrated consulting thank you yes of course um so what you're looking at on the existing conditions plan is this is the site as it exists today there is we're at the intersection of manheim pike and dillerville road there's also an entrance to the site along garfield two entrances along garfield and one along a private access easement that goes from manheim pike back to garfield avenue so the plan proposes the demolition of everything essentially from the right-of-way or the property line into the site and the rebuilding of everything new so if you could please lauren switch to sheet number four this would be our proposed site plan we are proposing a prototypical sheets 6139 square foot store there are perimeter parking in the total of 38 parking spaces we will have five dual-sided islands for a total of 10 fueling positions on the property none of the driveways are going to change their location so they will stay the same size the same width nothing will change there that allows us to not have to deal with pendot for the entrance off of manheim pike but to also just maintain that consistency with with folks that are used to coming in and out of the property and maintaining those driveway access points this store will have a drive-through that's located in the rear so you can see on the left side of the page or the west side there's a separate drive-through lane that'll have an order board and then you can kind of pull through there's a bypass area through there as well in terms of the shade tree commission we've attended their meeting and received their conditional approval as well as relief on some of the waivers that we're requesting tonight there are several waivers i believe five in total or four in total three of them relate to street trees and street lighting and the fourth relates to the preliminary plan submission procedures we are in receipt of our npds permit so we have that for the project and have coordinated with all the utilities obviously there's existing public utilities there today we'll be providing public utilities for the rebuild there is a storm water management facility on the north side of the building that will be handling the increase in impervious area for the project so we've received staff reviews as well as the cs davidson reviews for the project and are down to maybe just a few administrative items i think all the technical items at this point have been kind of ironed out so happy to talk about any of the waiver requests that we have or answer any questions i'll note that kelly brown with sheets is also here this evening so if there's anything procedurally with sheets that you have questions on she can certainly answer those as well
hi just a couple questions how old is the existing store that's on the site and i was wondering if you possible just to briefly summarize um how the current the new store differs from the current one is it going to be like a larger store does it have more pumps
the same is it so yeah in terms of the site perspective on that question it will be the 6139 foot store or square foot store which is slightly larger than what's out there today i don't have the exact square footage on the plan of of what that store is but i want to say it's around a thousand square foot larger just reconfigured it's their prototypical store now so what they're doing on the rebuild sites and kelly can certainly correct me if i'm speaking in in any way is just providing the updated store that will provide the same offerings here that you have down the road at one of the other remodels New Holland just did one for instance it'll be very similar to that in terms of this gas pumps I think this one has the two canopy now it'll go down to a single canopy they're doing that as well in all three models that helps with the larger building sometimes as well and just reconfiguring the way the site progresses with adding or you know kind of the site circulation with adding the drive through. In terms of the parking, let me double check. I think they are losing one double sided fuel island. So you lose two positions total. Great. Thank you very much. Yeah, of
course. Any other questions?
Free air pump to Yes, there'll be two free air machines on the on the site. That's important. Yeah. They try to get to anywhere they can i don't i think this one has one now it might have two but yeah they'll do two
i think you'd like to share on behalf of the city no they've worked very diligently and with many iterations of this plan to work through all of the technical comments and so the city is is happy
with where it is now great i do got some uh kerosene is still going to be an option at this store after the remodel is done no more kerosene losing a diesel pump fun fact i trained in this store uh it's a fun time uh just my only thing is keep the ice the same i don't like that nugget ice
that's the one store i can get the good ice at right okay well if we have no further comments
do i have a motion sorry can we just uh get a sense of the waivers that they're requesting
yeah i was gonna say that's um if you could read through the waivers and then the motion
is for um conditional approval so the first one is the preliminary plan submission procedure that just allows us to obviously proceed with the plan which was developed in accordance with all the requirements for a final plan instead of coming through the process twice street tree location that was due to and then the next one as well actually the tree quantity and spacing that's something that we went back and forth with the shade tree commission and with staff and the arborist very thoroughly um just due to the existing site we have the retaining wall along the front of the property there's overhead utilities underground utilities as well as pen dot not allowing us to put street trees along dillerville right outside of where the existing sidewalk is it's an obscure kind of parcel that is i should say right of way that's between dillerville and actually the property line of the store where there's an existing stormwater management basin that handles pendot runoff from some of the dillerville road reconfiguration that happened years and years ago so we did reach out to pendot for that we reached out to pendot as well to get some additional right-of-way along the frontage of the property in order to be able to put more trees in and they weren't willing to accept any more right-of-way along the frontage to try to meet that ordinance requirement so we kind of exhausted all the options that we came up with or collectively came up with with the staff and the consultants and again i think we we ended on a place where we're providing trees and other locations on the property to kind of meet the intent of the ordinance there and then the street lighting we went back and forth again on the street lighting as well so we're putting in two additional street lights that would be beyond the sheets property lighting that would help illuminate the intersection of garfield in the back of the store and the intersection of dillerville i'm sorry of manheim pike and that access that runs perpendicular to the property between the two sites so extra street lighting but we're still not meeting the total intent of the ordinance so
those were the requirements that we're asking where we thought and again this city satisfied
with where this is proceeding yes again um the they were at the shade i will i will speak for terry and say that they actually went to the shade tree commission twice and so they went through once and then they had to go back so um they have they've done their their best to really um to try to meet the requirements and it's really only um in their best attempts failing that that these waivers were necessary and are you able to get all
the required trees on the actual property or are there we do have a fee
in lieu of I think it's like 1,500 so there's maybe three trees or something that we weren't able to squeeze in again due to the constraints of utilities and things like that so there is a fee in lieu of I want to say it's 1,500 the DBH credits we were able to meet that portion of the requirements any other
question you did give a timeline the project okay completion maybe okay thank
you what do the employees do during the construction period you relocate them to different stores so the intention is to retain those employees okay if I don't have any further questions do I have a motion on the floor I would like to make
motion to conditionally approve the land development plan for 1180 manheim pike with the including the four requested waivers and modifications a second i have a motion and
a second all in favor oh i'm i didn't get kicked off with the oh yeah sorry i guess technically
we don't need Steven what I would say for this since this was started with Porter yeah voting that Porter votes on this and then we can shift back got it
that's what i would say mr sieben aye aye aye aye aye thank you very much any opposed
ayes have it can you just confirm amos did you do the motion oh no you did the motion did you do the second you did the second okay but hold on because if he's not a voting member
oh he can't do the second okay got it okay so all right i'm gonna put sorry so i have a motion on the floor do i have a second please second i have a motion and a second all in favor aye aye aye aye aye aye any opposed i have it thank you sorry okay exactly thank you nicole
appreciate that number four staff report to planning commission um so i was just going to give
a brief update on some of the plans that that we've been working on a bunch of things are starting to finalize the sheets plan has been a big one that we've been working on for a really long time many of you know that the mccaskey plan finally went off and they are working on that another big one that we are in the tail end of wrapping up is the 623 stevens avenue project so that's another thaddeus stevens foundation project they were here just probably a few weeks ago and so they're working on some of their final technical pieces before that can get out another update that i did want to provide because it was here a long time ago with regard to thaddeus stevens is the multi-use dorm that went through here we have not heard anything from them and we're assuming that this is due to state budget issues and so while it's a conditionally approved plan and we even have i believe the they were required in their conditions in addition to their developers agreement to have an mou with us regarding their tree placement i'm not sure how much of that you all remember we have like everything in hand but um we can't move forward because of the i believe it's because of the budget and so um that's what we're telling ourselves because why else would you just and so um and so that's been been um a big happening right now we have a couple of other things of course that we'll get to as part of the other business we've had some some work on minor plans as well with mosaic essentially create we created a minor plan for them for this interim period while they haven't been building on the site and so creating conditions for them to have to maintain the safety of the site and so that's just a it's a minor plan because it's essentially like an amendment to their regular plan so it did not have to come through planning commission but i did want you to know that that that is happening they did not file with the county which they were supposed to and so they had to backtrack and so even though they're all done with all of their city requirements they can't actually record it until they go through the county so that's also just sitting for a little while but just know that that's happening um and we were waiting to see when they're actually going to to build and so that minor plan covers them for two years um of not building and so and then has to be they have to essentially meet with us every six months to kind of update us on what the plan is moving forward with regard to building um i think those are the big ones does anybody have any questions about any plans that are lingering a quick question about mosaics i know part of their site
there's a 18th century building that's part of their project as part of that minor plan does that include making sure that they're maintaining that structure to ensure it doesn't deteriorate
over the two-year period that's a great question i don't think that that is part of the minor plan but it is on their property and so they would i mean as just part of it being your own parcel you would have to you would have to maintain it right so what can the public expect if
it were to come to be that mosaic never builds on the site um i'm not entirely sure they still own
the land and so it would be you know for them to determine what was going to happen with the land because whether or not the mosaic land development goes there willow valley owns the land right and so it it would just be kind of a redetermination they probably my guess is that they would either resubmit a different land development plan or they would sell it that would be my
okay assumption so i just want to make sure so the plan that's currently in place would expire and they'd need to go through the whole process again if they if the
the minor the minor plan they're in they have to abide by that for the two years and at the end they have to either tell us when they're going to build or provide us with a new plan okay thank you
betsy did you want to add anything yeah does that to your timeline extend the land development timeline or is that um trying to think of how like is it running concurrently or are they
so they have it kind of like veers off because they've already fallen out of their scheduled plan correct and so they're they're already out of compliance and so this essentially establishes a new time it resets a new timeline yeah and then i assume you could update us every six six months you said absolutely when i know something you'll know something right okay
thank you other business a public hearing sycamore ridge a public hearing to discuss the tentative plan for sycamore ridge is scheduled for september the 17th 2025 starting at 5 30.
this is this is just for remembering that the next meeting we will have a public hearing I wasn't sure if how frequently you guys have held public hearings and if you want some guidance on the process for that public hearing because there's different requirements that you would need to meet and because it's this PRD type requirement it has been advertised so it's required to be advertised twice we will have a court reporter here as required by the NPC to
document the conversation yeah we'll provide you some written beforehand I
don't have like a detailed account right now but I can definitely get you
information on so you have the ability to table it twice we haven't fully
finalized our comments yet but even with it being tabled twice I'm not sure if they'll be able to get to a point where it would be able to be approved conditionally within that time frame so you can take a vote or you can table it
so one thing one thing I don't I don't mean to remember for you did you have something more I don't want to interrupt you one thing to remember with this is that because it is a flexible residential development it differs a little bit from a land development because they can't get the same time extensions and so it has to adhere to the very specific timeline of a flexible residential development which is defined defined by zoning as opposed to by subdivision and land development it's a little bit different and so but because of that whereas another plan might be able to provide the city with an extension and i would actually say that that's more the norm than anything because generally speaking because plans have become so complicated it's very difficult to complete a review within the time frame of the mpc but because this is not a regular land development and it's a flexible flexible residential development we have to adhere to the time frame and that like that's a really important and pressing element of this because they cannot apply for an extension so we need to be careful not to bypass the timeline because then they would it would be a deemed acceptance which you don't want and so we have to take action within the time frame and so at each step you kind of have to evaluate okay like do they have so much to do that they're not going to be able to be in that time frame or is what they have in front of them something that they can complete and we'll table it and we'll have them come back and we'll see like what they've completed and determine if if at that point they think you think they can meet the the conditional approval and so and i would just say in addition to that to stress that every
time they come we need to advertise for it well that's not 100 correct so if it's tabled at the hearing then they they wouldn't need to re-advertise but we would need a court reporter at each hearing and you would have to just continue the public hearing so it would still be the same public hearing just continue so
and if i'm understanding the conditional approval would that give them approval to then finalize their plans and go into development
yes so it's the same as any other conditional approval with the added just reminder that generally speaking when the plans come to you for you know conditional and then final so if they come same thing like and they get conditional they essentially have a year to finalize that plan and so um again looking at the amount of comments we as a staff do our best to get them through many most of the technical comments so that the only the only things that they still have to do once they're conditionally approved are either like clerical or like you know paperwork sometimes they still need to have something figured out with a particular bureau or something but we know we're confident that it's on its way there um when we put it up for conditional approval so if it's anything extensive again you know because you're you're in this time frame right and so again there's no extensions happening so you just have to be very confident that they can accomplish what
needs to be accomplished i would also say so there are so as a flexible residential development they required to go through a tentative plan and a final plan versus a preliminary plan and a final plan but they are requesting that the tentative plan be combined as a tentative final like with
what sheets did today right so they're requesting that that be done yeah thank you and then b
a public hearing a data center pretty much the same so um today uh we received a memo from chris
Stelz the director of community planning and economic development it's before you and as part of the public hearing that you guys established for the data center on October 1st we need to determine an agenda so we can properly advertise what the what will be discussed as well as the action items because we'll have to get that advertisement in probably next week so I just wanted to have a discussion of what we'd like on the agenda as noted in the memo because planning commission has no authority over zoning matters or zoning interpretations the administration will not be participating in the public hearing so i'm not sure what all you would like to discuss as well as we have the the city council has requested staff to move forward with a draft text amendment for data centers so there will as listed in the memo there will be several public hearings coming up related to that and it would go before the draft ordinance we would anticipate going before you as a planning commission on october no sorry 15th so the second meeting in october so to clarify the public will have an
opportunity to attend the hearings at city council for other places correct yes and it's also going
before I don't think it's on here but it is was appealed the determination was appealed to the zoning hearing board so that's set for September 22nd agenda for
zoning hearing board and it seems that the city in this case believes that the Planning Commission's purpose for basically our position would make more sense if we worked in tandem with what City Council produces and have them essentially as the lead does that sound what they're essentially saying City Council took the lead on this they put pushed it through and now will be kind of their check and balance is that correct I mean it would be like any text
amendment to zoning ordinance if City Council requests is it then it would go to you guys for review and recommendations it's it's a zoning text amendment is not something Planning Commission has they can only make recommendation you don't have like deciding ability to like make a determination or decide that so it would be like any other text amendment that we would have where we'd prepare it it would go to County Planning Commission
as well for review and on that date that it comes to us the public will still
have their full rights to speak yeah it would be still be a public meeting it wouldn't be a public hearing so we wouldn't have to advertise it as such it be advertised when it's a public hearing for City Council which is our standard but it would be a public meeting and it would be on the agenda that it was going to be a discussion item and also we wouldn't have to do a separate advertisement outlining the agenda and we wouldn't have to get a court reporter if we don't have it as a public hearing
I mean as I recall when we were talking about setting up public hearing really wasn't done with the intention that we would actually impact or change the zoning decision I recall it really being that we just needed to learn more about how the decision was made so I don't think there was any disillusionment on this body that we were somehow going to you know reverse the zoning officers decision at that hearing or our impact you know the course of what was already done at that hearing I think we were just interested in giving the public an opportunity to understand because as we all know land use decisions land use and zoning is not always one a topic that's easily understood by the public is because it's very niche and often obscure process to the layperson so now the question in my mind is now is that something I think this we should still engaging on some level you know it's just you know having staff explain how the decision was made just so the public has an understanding of how it was made is that something that is worth going through the additional work of setting up a public hearing or can that just be a briefing item at a future regular meeting so the public can still have that information on how the decision was accomplished how the decision was made so necessarily going through the
additional October 15th meeting which would be a regular meeting at that point we would also have a lot more information ourselves because again as Betsy noted it the the person who's appealing the decision that was made by the zoning officer that's happening September 22nd so that will have happened at that point and um there will have been also opportunities through city council again as the letter points out um it's going to council committee on october 6th so council committee means that there won't be a public comment period on it but it will be on the agenda and then um and then it will come to come to us on the 15th so there will be plenty of opportunities for people to attend meetings and learn about the process and the correct um avenue through which this this is supposed to travel sorry i think that's me but what i what i will say and that i do think is really important to note here for you all is that i i do feel like between city council and here it started right and so i think that the city heard you and heard the public with what happened at our last meeting and at the city council meeting so i think that one thing you can take to heart is that what is now starting to happen in zoning and in student and in city council is you know part and partial for the fact that it you know people came here so i think that
that's something yeah i just wanted to uh kind of support uh what um porter was saying you know i think the idea was to get information about how this decision was made i think it's disappointing to me that the administration has chosen not uh to engage with that us on that i agree you know with this letter that obviously zoning we don't have authority over zoning but it is of our interest to know how our zoning code is being interpreted and how that process works so um you know i i am hopeful that some of that information will come out at the zoning hearing board um i again been disappointed the administration's not sharing any of that information uh i checked the you know the frequently asked questions uh page again there's no mention of the you know use not provided for that is in the zoning code that could have been applied in this case there's been no information about why that wasn't applied so that's what i was hoping to get out of a hearing um you know but if the administration is not going to participate i would agree with uh with porter at least having you know at our maybe it's the october meeting or later after we have the information that was shared the zoning hearing board for us to better understand how those decisions were made i also want to say i think i think it has not been like it's been confusing both in the reporting of lmp and the council meeting when we're talking about the zoning amendment there folks think that this is going to apply to the current projects and i don't see that i don't see any avenue for that and again it feels like we're not being transparent about that i mean we would probably have a lot more people here tonight if they knew that was the case so i think it's really important that the administration is clear about what that zoning amendment can and cannot do and again we just haven't seen much transparency on those issues so some of this um you know i think there's two separate things here definitely supporting the the zoning amendment you need to be clear that that does not apply uh to the the current projects um and then i still think we need answers about how this original decision was made and if we don't get that at the zoning hearing board um
you know we need to find other ways to get at that information i'm also gonna agree with mr
stolzbus and mr stevens over here um i'm open to the idea of not having a public hearing if we're not going to get the participation of the administration which i also think is a disappointment uh disservice to the residents of the city of lancaster who want transparency i feel like what we were doing as many or yeah i'll say many of us up here have been saying uh we've been in the pursuit of information um so i do want to call to light uh what number is this a h of our powers um requests from other departments and agencies of the city all information available which relates to the work of the commission i think it's important for us in the process of drafting this new zoning ordinance to also reflect on the conversations that have occurred between the developer and city zoning and i'm an open government guy i know that that sometimes is a little bit worrisome in government because a lot of information information overload but i feel like the public deserves to see the documentation that has been for example provided to lmp i believe through right to know requests and hopefully have that information available to the public ideally accessible on the faq page for the data center on its website prior to the zoning hearing board meeting because this is ultimately residents as far as i understand it currently this is residents speaking their interests trying to do what they can to have an impact in their community and i feel what we can do is this body is give them as much information as possible to equip them for the argument that they have to make before this quasi-judicial body so i do feel that we should at least exercise ah and request these prior conversations between the developer and our city zoning office and make those documents available to the public i'll put my two cents in
as well um agreed i don't think we need a public hearing but and especially because i think the public may be confused about our role but i do think we should keep it as an agenda item possibly on that october first meeting for having it um still just to allow for it to be part of the conversation again in lieu of a public hearing i mean i would agree with that
i mean i think it needs to be something that we continue just again just just to be able to provide information to the public about what the city is doing i mean i think as uh lauren and as staff has already uh shared there there are irons in the fire um that the city is has responded to public input here and i think it's important that we highlight that so we don't get the wrong impression that you know we had that one big meeting and then there's just silence I think it'd be helpful you know in the very least having some kind of memo like this drawn up to that summarizes you know all the information behind what was done so at least that we can see it and we can and it can be potentially shared you know if that can be shared with the public you know if something like this is how the administration get comfortable with at sharing some outline some summary of the process that was done to arrive at the zoning decision you know i think that's still certainly a step in the right direction even if it may not completely satisfy you know what we're interested in seeing or what residents might be interested in seeing so i think if you know the administration could just summarize in a memo you know here's what was considered here's the steps we took here's how we arrived at where housing versus use is not provided for i think that would really be really really helpful so i'd certainly encourage you know something like that to be drafted um over the next next month or so um so that we can have it on hand prior to considering the uh ordinance yes i can just without being redundant i can just
say i'm in support of the commissioner's um requests in terms of this data center and the hearing you know I think it's important for the transparency you know I think the character of this commission we thrive and we respect transparency so I think that's important we want to make sure that that's that continues to go
forward in light of transparency are we able to put this schedule that's on the bullet on the faq page just so it's easily accessible by the public to be able to see when these milestones are being met and to know when um key participation opportunities will present themselves what does it mean you can check like is that like a hard process is there
I would like to even though we don't have 75 people in attendance today to talk about it I would like just to note it so that is somehow on a record that we did receive the memo today as was stated before literally right before the meeting and the third paragraph of it in case the memo is not made public it just reads like this the administrative the administration is also aware of the city planning commission's decision to hold its own hearing on october 1st to address the initial zoning determination regarding data centers while i which would be chris delts the director fully understand planning commissioners desire to engage on this important topic the planning commission does not have the authority does not have any authority regarding matters of zoning interpretation and then the last sentence as such the administration will not participate in this hearing i just think it's important just to hear those words because it's so final and i don't it really rubs me the wrong way as it has everyone else here and it diminishes who we are and although we may not have the authority for that one thing as everyone else has said this matters so it's it just seems strongly awarded for something that we could have maybe nuanced a little bit better it rubs me the wrong way a little bit
too because again it's misstating i think what our intent was we were not intending to try to exercise an authority we all know we don't have we're just trying to get information and create a venue that where that information can be shared with the public so i think you know stating that you know we don't have the authority to have anything related to zoning interpretation that was not our intention so obviously there's always room for misinterpretation when we're going through many different lanes of communication but
um yeah i agree with your sentiment i mean i'll ask the uh voting members of the commission tonight if any of them are interested in making a motion to request um to us in like a packet form for our next meet at least to have for our next meeting if not discuss uh any materials provided to LMP reporters via right to know requests regarding the issue of the
data center or if that's not legally feasible kind of a memo summarizing the
process no I mean no I think a memo still would be good like summarizing but to the point that there is a resident who has their own case to make before the zoning hearing board the original documentation and for two reasons one them having that to reflect on is like this is what it was not a summary of what it was but also then if we are if we have this stack of material before us yeah it's a lot to go through but I feel like it will give a more thorough understanding of the conversations that occurred with what I feel is a lack of transparency here I personally do not feel comfortable relying on summary memos but I'm okay with them being supplementary to the materials we might
receive I guess I'm just unclear of what materials exactly you would like to
receive any information provided to LMP reporters you can do that through a right to know request as well we can do it through a right to know request as well but we can also do
it as a body i would i would say just receive in memo form a written summary of the process that was used to make the determination by the zoning officer is that is that like kind of a level because i can appreciate that there needs to be a level of specificity to make our request
feasible i don't know if that's if that's a better i think i'll toss that one to betsy because i think that you're you're asking something of the director of our department and so that's who wrote the this memo and so you're it's my understanding that you're asking for something that outlines how the zoning decision was made and why one decision was made and not another if that is in fact what you're asking for that i like i don't have the authority sure to tell you whether or not one that is something that you can ask for or two whether you're going to get it sure
there's no stack of papers i mean again and i don't and i don't mean to simplify but this was a decision that was made by a person in their job in their official capacity this is what his profession is as a zoning officer yes there were alternatives absolutely so he could have chosen to use this at to to describe this as use is not provided for fully acknowledged but in his capacity as the zoning officer the decision was made so i'm not i guess i'm struggling to understand what more there is to be provided because it was it was a decision made it was a professional decision that was made and so what what more is there in the process so yes there is the information that was provided to the zoning officer so there's that background information so he received background information and based on that background information he made the decision and then that's and then he wrote the letter so that's like that is literally
the chain of evidence so i think whether we like it or not there is an interpretation factor to any rule of law so clearly that you know we all may not like the decision that occurred with this data center but i think what we should stop at this point i don't believe there's anything we can do to it we i think we need to move forward and i think we need to look at how we can affect and influence these projects moving forward in a way that is positive for both our community and our environment as well as our economic you know output so i think as much as it would have been great to have somebody from the zoning officer come up and educate us on this process in maybe more details than what we're able to garner i i think that miss finn has done a great job of kind of setting that stage for us ultimately i think that there is some disappointment here because this was the community came out in ways that we have not seen which i think was emotionally moving but ultimately the authority lies in what it is so again whether we like it or not interpretation is part of it um i think we take the educational opportunity and we redirect um some of our efforts on how can we ensure that moving forward we're supporting the community we're hearing their needs and we're actually making a difference that's where i think we
really need to place our energy and our effort okay mr chair would it be appropriate to make a motion to cancel the public hearing portion of the october 1st meeting because right now it is scheduled and i think with all that would have to take place between now and that meeting we should probably just make it official to say we're canceling that portion of our meeting so they don't go through the efforts of advertising hiring a court stenographer and
reporter and all of this are we able to add um an exception to that that the dates with it that are noted within this memo will be clearly communicated to the public so their opportunity to participate is easy enough for everybody to understand like i want everybody who was here two weeks ago to know that october 6 this is happening october 10th these are happening not all are pertinent to them but i think it's essential that we communicate this process and that they have a very easy way to understand what is happening and when they can participate i think that's
reasonable we could craft that as one motion yeah yeah is that yeah i think you should do one motion to cancel the public hearing portion of the meeting and say that it will in that motion you can cancel the public hearing and also um include that you would like for the item to still be on the agenda and then i would do a second motion to say that um you would like for the information that was the dates that were published in the memo regarding the process going forward for the data center to be published online does that make sense can i ask a question
can this memo be made public or is that not do we have a motion on the floor okay mr chair i would
like okay mr i didn't mean to say it that way but i would like to make a motion then to cancel the public hearing portion of our october 1st meeting but to still leave as an agenda item open to the discussion of what we have talked about today I just like to speak
very briefly just to clarify I think some of my earlier comments and questions that my only purpose really to suggest some of the things we talked about was really in the interest of public education I certainly did not want to give the impression that was in any way trying to undermine the credibility of staff i know you'll work extraordinarily hard and i certainly i may not have agreed with the decision made by the zoning officer totally appreciate that he made that in his professional capacity and speaking as someone who has sat on the other side of that desk i know that is rarely an easy thing to do so i just really want to emphasize that my interest in making some of suggestions i made earlier was really in the interest of public education just to help the public understand how some of these processes work because it's not always immediately apparent so i do apologize if some of my comments gave the impression that i was trying to dig for something that could undermine the credibility of staff i know we are extraordinarily fortunate in this city to have an incredibly talented and hard-working group of people supporting the work that we do so i just wanted to make sure that was on the record and i do apologize again if any of my comments seem to suggest otherwise that's excellent question all in favor
let it know by saying aye aye aye aye aye aye opposed ayes have it motion carried i would like
to make a motion to clearly communicate to the public the project timeline for the data center
text amendment i'll second motion on the floor in a second ready for the question discussion all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye aye aye opposed ayes have it motion carried
so like so do you mind if i i don't want i don't want to get away from my head um i appreciate
what you said ms sufert about you know essentially community cooperation what we can do with more foresight um i there's two points to make and what i have to say i agree with you but i think the thing holding us back the most and i've said this for more than a year now is our lack of updates to the zoning code since we adopted the comprehensive plan i'm very upset that we are in this position in part because i feel somewhat responsible that we haven't done that work yet i don't fully understand why i respected uh the hecticness we experienced as a body and as a city with the departure of douglas after that moment but i feel like some of that work is the foresight we need to have for these things going forward we are in a specific situation right now though um as someone who works in municipal government i do respect the qualifications and experience of other municipal staff and other municipalities um but the thing that bothers me the most and why i want to know the background information is because a persuasion a persuasive argument for something that wasn't explicitly given in our zoning ordinance had to be made and as respectfully as i can say this i really want to understand why this data storage processing center is considered under the warehousing and storage use which explicitly excludes processing i understand that processing in different contexts has different impacts but it's very important to me to understand what case was made to make that reasonable in the eyes of our zoning officer and that's why i'm so dead set on trying to
understand the background information to that decision i want to echo commissioner dastra and maybe request like can we just have a standing agenda item where it's an update on where we're at with updating the zoning code because i feel like we go kind of months without hearing and i think it's really important for us that to be front and center for this body um are these consulting firms local national then do we have a sense of the timeline for the upper update
is there a goal that the city has in order to get some of this um you know work underway from
a timeline perspective and remind me when your proposals are due and when is the decision being
made and then following the awarding of that project will it kick off immediately or is that pending the schedules that the consultants have do you think the speed of the like ability of the consultant to get to work would influence that decision at all or is that decision solely going to be made based on cost qualifications what are you and uh do you know um i'm not sure if you would know this or not but i know that there's quite a few developments that have been in the works and that are kind of taking a step back from a progression standpoint and i'm just curious to know um do you think any of those projects are being like um held up just maybe because of current economic situations or do you think that like as the zoning ordinance particularly in the mixed use development um and the parking requirements that would be associated with that is do you think that some are waiting for this and would you have any idea how many no no just like any projects that are happening within the city that may like i know that there was an i know one specifically is kind of like waiting for um to get started on their project because they're waiting for the new mixed use zoning code to be adopted because of the parking requirements based off of the so i was just curious to know if there was any other developers who were in that similar situation that are just kind of standing by waiting for these things to
occur I would also add to that that we have residences online that are not filling and so I think that there's also right and so right so but it's kind of like a circular domino effect right because if they're they're not filling so they're not building more it depends on what the builder wants to be building is he building are they building a market rate apartment if they're building a market rate apartment and they're not filling and there are three other market rate apartments that have open units and the cost of construction is high and you know and and and and and I think that it's it becomes a
waiting game yeah and I'll close with one final statement I think it would be great as a group to kind of come back and maybe huddle up I don't know what you want to call it on the comprehensive plan it's just been a while since I I think we've kind of discussed the goals, objectives, and I think just to realign everybody as we continue those processes, it would be really helpful to kind of have like a one-on-one run-through of that at a future agenda meeting, or at a future commission meeting soon.
All right, and I also have my final statement. I do, I wanna just, you know, I think it's good that we're holding off on the hearing. I think it's good that we're keeping the data center as an agenda item, and I think we should revisit the idea of requesting a memo. mean i don't think it is i don't think it's as simple as the zoning officer makes a decision like this in his professional expertise i mean we know that zoning officer consults with council you know i think in i had heard in previous administration that if there is a project of this magnitude you know there would be conversations within the department the mayor in previous administrations would sometimes be engaged in those conversations so i think it is very important for us to have more information about how these types of decisions are made I don't think it's quite as simple as one person made it and now we have to live with it so again I think I'm supportive of the progress we're making but I do think we should if depending on what kind of information shared at the zoning hearing board reconsider requesting a memo I do not
mean to oversimplify of course the zoning officer consulted with the city solicitor as well as additional attorneys I mean it wasn't nobody operates in a vacuum in City Hall so for sure there were other meetings what I meant to imply was more that there's not a huge paper trail and so there is process and there were discussions but if you're looking for a paper trail that
you're not gonna find which is also why it's really important just to have
information any public comment Taylor Taylor Taylor yep so that memo that you received I while we were sitting here I was trying to look online to see if it was made public made available to the public and I can't find it so where would I be able to see that or is it not actually available to the public at the
on it it's not been made public yet we received it this evening any other
public comment hearing none do I have a motion to adjourn second motion to adjourn in a second question all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye opposed ayes have it motion carried meeting adjourned thank you thank you thank you for coming